<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<page title="betterForm Home" id="index">
    <news>
        <headline date="June, 25 2009" id="important">
            <subtitle>
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=20274&amp;package_id=16465&amp;release_id=570513" target="_blank">betterForm Core 1.5.0 released</a>
            </subtitle>
            <para>betterForm 3.0.0b2 is ready. This is mainly a quality release with hundreds of improvements. betterForm now passes 86% of the normative tests of the XForms 1.1E1 test suite.</para>
        </headline>
        <headline date="December, 19 2008" id="important">
            <subtitle>
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=20274&amp;package_id=16465&amp;release_id=570513" target="_blank">betterForm Core 1.5.0 released</a>
            </subtitle>
            <para>betterForm Web 3.0.0b1 is out. Completely renewed with new JavaScript layer, improved XForms 1.1 support, localisation, XPath 2.0 and more.</para>
        </headline>
        <headline date="August, 19 2008" id="important">
            <subtitle>
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=20274&amp;package_id=16465&amp;release_id=570513" target="_blank">betterForm Core 1.5.0 released</a>
            </subtitle>
            <para>BetterForm, the modular XForms processor has released a new Core version featuring migration to Saxon for XPath 2.0 support, many XForms 1.1 functions as well as further new XForms 1.1 features.</para>
        </headline>

    </news>
    <teaser name="main">
        <teaser name="web3">
           <title>
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=20274&amp;package_id=16465&amp;release_id=570513" target="_blank">betterForm 3.0.0b2 released</a>
            </title>
            <para>
                betterForm 3 is a new major release of the betterForm XForms 1.1 implementation, coming with a brand new
                JavaScript layer, improved XForms 1.1 support, localisation, XPath 2.0 and more.
            </para>
            <para>
                - betterForm is now using Dojo Toolkit Version 1.2.3 (latest) which vastly improves the quality of the UI.
                The completely rewritten JavaScript layer already comes with compilation and CDN support allowing you
                to load many parts of the application libs from Google. Dojo components can be seemlessly integrated
                with XForms processing to add the last missing pieces that make up a full application.
            </para>
            <para>
                - Large parts of the Core processor and the Web layer have been heavily refactored and now provide a
                cleaner API and simplified parts of the Code. Extensibility of the Java API has been greatly improved.
            </para>
            <para>
                - The CSS system has been reworked for consistency and there's new documentation available.
            </para>
            <para>
                - Conformance has been improved and now betterForm passes 86% of the XForms 1.1E1 Test Suite.
            </para>
        
        </teaser>
        <title>What is it ?</title>
        <para id="intro">
            <list>
                <item>a ToolKit combining XForms, AJAX and the Dojo toolkit</item>
                <item>combines an attractive and extensible set of cross-browser widgets with the rich MVC Model of XForms</item>
                <item>Rapid web application building in a declarative way</item>
                <item>see <a href="demo.html">demos</a> for a first impression of betterForm</item>
            </list>
        </para>

        <title>Screenshoots</title>
        <para>
            <a id="screen1" href="resources/images/Select1ScreenShot.png" target="_blank"><img src="resources/images/Select1ScreenShotSmall.png" alt="Select 1" border="0" halign="left" /></a>
            <a id="screen2" href="resources/images/RepeatScreenShot.png" target="_blank"><img src="resources/images/RepeatScreenShotSmall.png" alt="Select 1" border="0" halign="right" /></a>
        </para>

        <para style="display:block;"></para>

        <title>Key Components</title>

        <subtitle>XForms</subtitle>
        <para>
	    betterForm is an Open Source Java Implementation of the W3C XForms standard 'that represents the next generation of forms for the Web'. [Abstract of the XForms PR]
        </para>

<!--
        <para>
	    XForms purpose and justification might be explained best by the official statements in the Specification:
        </para>
        <cite from=" [Chapter 1.1 of the XForms PR]">
	    Forms are an important part of the Web, and they continue to be the primary means for enabling interactive Web applications. Web applications and electronic commerce solutions have sparked the demand for better Web forms with richer interactions. XForms 1.0 is the response to this demand, and provides a new platform-independent markup language for online interaction between a person (through an XForms Processor) and another, usually remote, agent. XForms are the successor to HTML forms, and benefit from the lessons learned from HTML forms.
        </cite>
        <para>
        For more information on XForms its highly recommended to look at the official XForms homepage at
            <a href="http://www.w3.org/Markup/forms" target="_blank">http://www.w3.org/Markup/forms</a>.
        </para>
-->

        <subtitle>AJAX</subtitle>
        <para>
            betterForm uses <a href="http://directwebremoting.org">Direct Web Remoting DWR</a> to connect Javascript widgets and containers such as repeat, switch and group to the XForms engine.
            For page authors absolutely no knowledge of AJAX techniques is required. All the wiring is automatic.
        </para>
<!--
        <para>
            An EventQueue on the server will gather all notifications and send them back in a network-optimized way reducing size and amount of message to the bare minimum.
        </para>
        <para>
            The Server push (reverse AJAX) capabilities of DWR allow to build effective multi-user applications with share the same data and get instant notifications of data changes.
        </para>
        <para>
            Java programmers can easily hook into their own classes on the server for adding additional application services which can directly be called from Javascript.
        </para>
-->

        <subtitle>The Dojo Toolkit</subtitle>
        <para>
            The <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org">Dojo toolkit</a> is one of the most well-known and highest-quality Javascript libraries around and receives
            a lot of attention and credits. It provided the ideal foundation for building a Javascript API to support the XForms capabilities of betterForm.
        </para>
<!--
        <para>
            Like XForms Dojo supports a declarative approach to build advanced user interfaces and offers a <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/book/dojo-book-0-9/part-2-dijit/dijit-glance">rich set</a>
            of accessible widgets and advanced layout containers. It's easy and natural to mix and match plain Dojo/Dijit with XForms-enabled controls.
        </para>
        <para>
            Using Dojo does not constrain the usage of other Javascript libraries and components. The Dojo package loader allows to integrate any Javascript without trouble.
        </para>
-->

    </teaser>
    <subtitle>Key features of betterForm</subtitle>
    <list id="features">
        <item title="Advanced UIs">
            By bundling the Dojo Toolkit it's now possible to use the full set of Dojo controls to build
            application-like UIs with full AJAX and XForms support without needing to write a single line of script
            or Java code.
        </item>
        <item title="Styling">
            A complete, fine-grained system of CSS classes allows to control the layout and styling of
            the whole UI. A quick reference card shows all classes available on one sheet.
        </item>
        <item title="minimal-intrusive">
            The betterForm architecture is minimal-intrusive. There's no coding needed to integrate XForms processing
            into your webapp while still giving you a lot of hooks when tied integration is wanted.
        </item>
        <item title="zero-install">
            There are no plugins or other installations needed to use full XForms in your browser today. It will work
            for the major browsers (IE6.0+, Safari 3.0+, FF 2.0+ and others).
        </item>
        <item title="REST">
            As HTTP handling and full XML support are built-in it's a matter of minutes to connect a betterForm page to
            a REST service. XForms is an ideal fit when working with such architectures.
        </item>
        <item title="XRX">
            betterForm nicely supports the XForms Rest XQuery (XRX) paradigm. XQueries can directly be used as data and
            parameterized through your XForms. betterForm  nicely integrates with the popular Open Source XML database
            <a href="exist.sourceforge.net">eXist</a>.
        </item>
        <item title="noscript fallback">
            In restricted environments often JavaScript is filtered or prohibited. betterForm forms will continue to work
            the best way a request/response interface can give you.
        </item>
        <item title="components">
            It's easy to integrate new components and enhance the set of available controls. Not only all Dojo controls
            might be used but additionally any JavaScript can be integrated and used under the package loading system
            of Dojo thereby getting the advantages of JavaScript compilation, compression and layering of scripts.
        </item>
        <item title="typing, validation and calculation">
            Data typing will come to your pages by simple declarations. The
            full set of XML Schema types plus your own extensions can be used. XForms constraints allow to apply further
            facets to any data node. Along with the capability to execute calculations in a similar declarative way
            you never have to worry about invalid data in your backend again.
        </item>
        <item title="declarative application building">
            Both XForms and Dojo follow a declarative approach to page building. This is a perfect match - both can co-exist
            with interference and interact in a controlled manner. No manual scripting will be needed unless you like
            to write your own components.
        </item>
        <item title="Connectors">
            Usually some sort of persistence backend will make your apps powerful and you'll need to seemlessly
            integrate with arbritary datasources. betterForm already supports the most common protocols but can also
            be easily extended to dock to any datasource. These connectors can be plugged by configuration and
            can be combined with any other connector in a page.
       </item>
        <item title="Open Source License">
            Starting with betterForm Web 3.0.0b1 betterForm will be available under the liberal BSD and Apache 2 licenses. This
            allows unlimited commercial use. Professional support will be available from the admins of the project.
            Please contact us.
        </item>
    </list>

<!--
    <subtitle>Distributions</subtitle>
    <list>
        <item>
            <b>betterForm Core</b> - provides a Java implementation of XForms as a JavaBean component
        </item>
        <item>
            <b>betterForm Web</b> - integrate the betterForm processor in a Servlet environment with full AJAX support
        </item>
        <item>
            <b>Chicoon</b> - integrates betterForm with Cocoon. This makes XForms processing available to the Cocoon platform
        </item>
        <item>
            <b>Convex</b> - clientside Java Applet integration running on IE6
        </item>
    </list>
-->

<!--
    <subtitle>Documentation</subtitle>
    <para>
        <img src="images/pdf.gif"/>
        <a href="BetterFormCookBook.pdf">betterForm Cookbook</a> (out of sync currently)
    </para>
    <para>Comments welcome.</para>
-->
   
    <subtitle id="supported">Supported by</subtitle>
    <para>
        <table>
            <tr>
                <td width="25%">
                    <span>
                        <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/"
                           style="display:block; width:88px; height:31px; border:0; margin:0;padding:0;text-decoration:none;text-indent:0;">
                            <img src="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/opensource/img/banners/idea88x31_white.gif"
                                 alt="The best Java IDE" border="0"/>
                        </a>
                    </span>

                </td>
                <td width="25%">
                </td>                
                <td width="50%">
                    <div align="left" style="font-size:9pt;border:thin solid;margin:1px;padding:5px;">
                        YourKit is kindly supporting open source projects with its full-featured Java Profiler.
                        YourKit, LLC is the creator of innovative and intelligent tools for profiling
                        Java and .NET applications. Take a look at YourKit's leading software products:
                        <a href="http://www.yourkit.com/java/profiler/index.jsp">YourKit Java Profiler</a> and
                        <a href="http://www.yourkit.com/.net/profiler/index.jsp">YourKit .NET Profiler</a>.
                    </div>
                </td>
            </tr>
        </table>

    </para>
</page>
